<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>motorcycle on Sophie&#39;s Space</title>
    <link>https://sophieis.lgbt/tags/motorcycle/</link>
    <description>Read the latest  motorcycle on Sophie&#39;s Space</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>me@sophi.ee (Sophie 🌸)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>me@sophi.ee (Sophie 🌸)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 15:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sophieis.lgbt/tags/motorcycle/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Building a information display for my CRF250L</title>
      <link>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2020-11-21-building-a-information-display-for-my-crf250l/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>me@sophi.ee (Sophie 🌸)</author>
      <guid>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2020-11-21-building-a-information-display-for-my-crf250l/</guid>
      <description>One of the small handful of motorcycles I own is a 2015 Honda CRF250L. I bought it after doing the Monkey Run Morocco in 2019 (maybe I should write about that one day&amp;hellip;) and realising this whole off road / adventure motorcycling thing is a lot of fun.
The CRF250L is an excellent beginners adventure bike. It&amp;rsquo;s lightweight, easy to ride and decent off road. It&amp;rsquo;s not an Africa Twin by any stretch, but for someone like me who is starting out, it&amp;rsquo;s great.</description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[ <p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/assembled-version.jpg" alt="Header Image"  />
</p>
<p>One of the small handful of motorcycles I own is a 2015 Honda CRF250L. I bought it after doing the Monkey Run Morocco in 2019 (maybe I should write about that one day&hellip;) and realising this whole off road / adventure motorcycling thing is a lot of fun.</p>
<p>The CRF250L is an excellent beginners adventure bike. It&rsquo;s lightweight, easy to ride and decent off road. It&rsquo;s not an Africa Twin by any stretch, but for someone like me who is starting out, it&rsquo;s great.</p>
<p>That said, there is room for improvement. The bike had a few choice mods when I bought it. Things like a smaller front sprocket (for a bit more low down torque), aftermarket air filter, bar risers, heated grips, hand guards, foldable mirrors and a rear rack.</p>
<p>One of the things I disliked about the bike was how basic its dash was. It has no tach and no temp gauge. You get speed, fuel, time and some lights&hellip; that&rsquo;s it.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/dash-stock.jpg" alt="stock-dash"  />
</p>
<p>It has an over-temp light, and obviously you don&rsquo;t <em>need</em> a tachometer, but it is nice to have a better idea of what the bike is doing.</p>
<p>I wondered if, being a somewhat modern bike, there would be some sort of diagnostic port that I could connect to to get this data. As it turns out, there is!</p>
<p>&ldquo;Modern&rdquo; Honda motorcycles have a 4 pin connector called a HDS port. This is <em>similar</em> in function to the OBD port in a car. In fact that was one of the first approaches I looked in to, after finding <a href="https://www.lonelec.co.uk/Honda-4pin-OBD2-Adaptor">HDS to OBD adapter</a> cables online.</p>
<p>After further research (huge shout-out to the <a href="http://forum.pgmfi.org/">PGM-FI forums</a>) found that Honda does use a standard protocol (KWP2000), but most cheap ELM327 OBD adaptors (including the one I had) are incompatible with it, as it has a non-standard initialisation sequence. I did try it anyway, after making a cable (aka jamming some wires into the HDS port and clipping them to the ELM327 device) I was able to confirm it didn&rsquo;t work.</p>
<p>So I kept looking and stumbled across two things that made me realise this was possible. The first was the <a href="https://gonzos.net/projects/ctx-obd/">CTX-OBD</a> project that had a similar goal/idea to what I was hoping to do. The second was the KWP2000 library for arduino that Aster94 had on <a href="https://github.com/aster94/Keyword-Protocol-2000">GitHub</a>.</p>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t end up using the KWP2000 library (as it&rsquo;s only been implemented for Suzuki) but I did use the hardware (namely a <a href="https://www.st.com/resource/en/datasheet/l9637.pdf">L9637D</a> bus driver)</p>
<p>I was able to finally prove the theory with some very ropey code, an Arduino Nano and the L9637D.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/ardu-nano.jpg" alt="ardu nano"  />
</p>
<p>Once the excitement of seeing data from my bike&rsquo;s ECU being displayed on my laptop, I  had to think about how I would build the actual device.</p>
<p>For the display, I decided to use an cheap ILI9341 SPI display, as they are easy to work with and I had a few laying about. For the microcontroller I went with an ESP32. I could&rsquo;ve used the Arduino Nano, but the ESP gives me a <em>much</em> faster CPU, more memory, more peripherals and the option to use things like WiFi and Bluetooth in the future. They are also incredibly cheap and I had a few of them kicking around.</p>
<p>I put together a prototype using the ESP32, a display and the L9637D chip.</p>
<p>After much tweaking it all worked and I knew the design was viable, so I designed a PCB in Eagle CAD. I sent it over to PCBWay for fab (my first time using them) and a week or so later these turned up.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/pcbs.jpg" alt="pcbs"  />
</p>
<p>I was very happy with the PCBs. They did have a small mistake, which was entirely my fault and only required cutting a trace. After fixing that and soldering everything on, I was able to flash the firmware I&rsquo;d written and it was ready to go. I added a few more features like an external temperature sensor (using a DHT22) and a GPS module for speed/heading/etc.</p>
<p>I needed a case, so designed something basic in Fusion360 and 3D printed it. I decided to go with a generic GoPro style mount on the bottom, which I paired with a handlebar mount I had to mount it to the bike.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/assembled-version.jpg" alt="assembled-version"  />
</p>
<p>I mounted it to the bike, and lo and behold, it worked! I took the bike for a ride and discovered a few bugs in the firmware (like the speed being reported in KPH not MPH) but it actually worked!</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>I have done a much more technical write-up on the project&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/mickwheelz/Honda-Motorcycle-Dash">GitHub repo</a>, which includes a wiki.</p>
<p>So whats next? Well I&rsquo;ve designed a version 2 of the PCB, which has simpler power delivery, and uses a display directly mounted to it. I will cover this new version in a future blog! I also need to do some more work on the firmware, and the documentation, which will come in time.</p>
<p>This should work on other Honda bikes, so if you&rsquo;ve got a Honda made in the last 10 years or so, and give it a try please do let me know how you go!</p>
 ]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
