<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Sophie&#39;s Space</title>
    <link>https://sophieis.lgbt/</link>
    <description>Read the latest on Sophie&#39;s Space</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>me@sophi.ee (Sophie 🌸)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>me@sophi.ee (Sophie 🌸)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 11:30:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sophieis.lgbt/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hacking cat printers for fun and... likes on twitter?</title>
      <link>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2022-04-23-hacking-cat-printers-for-fun-and-likes-on-twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 11:30:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>me@sophi.ee (Sophie 🌸)</author>
      <guid>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2022-04-23-hacking-cat-printers-for-fun-and-likes-on-twitter/</guid>
      <description>Allow me to introduce you to this&amp;hellip;
This amazing piece of technology is a cat printer. It is a small, battery powered, monochrome thermal printer that is able to be controlled over Bluetooth Low Energy.
It&amp;rsquo;s designed to portable for use with your smartphone. With it, you can print your photos on the go, just like a polaroid! (but way worse)
Here is an example:
Original Image Cat Printer Hold up, what?</description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[ <p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/cat-printer.png" alt="Header Image"  />
</p>
<p>Allow me to introduce you to this&hellip;</p>
<p>This amazing piece of technology is a cat printer. It is a small, battery powered, monochrome thermal printer that is able to be controlled over Bluetooth Low Energy.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s designed to portable for use with your smartphone. With it, you can print your photos on the go, just like a polaroid! (but way worse)</p>
<p>Here is an example:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Original Image</th>
<th>Cat Printer</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/monkey.jpg" alt=""  />
</td>
<td>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/car-printer-monkey.jpg" alt=""  />
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h3 id="hold-up-what-why">Hold up, what? why?</h3>
<p>Who wouldn&rsquo;t want to print their photos in glorious 1 bit dithered monochrome?!</p>
<p>One of my favourite <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EW8svX5OErc">youtubers</a> had covered similar ones, and I then saw one of my <a href="https://twitter.com/xssfox/status/1421271256205201409">friends</a> tweet about it. How could I say no to such a glorious device?</p>
<p>Objectively crappy output aside, the prints do have a certain aesthetic to them that I like.</p>
<p>But, truth be told, I bought the cat printer mostly because it seemed like a fun thing to play with. But, as it turns out, it was quite hackable.</p>
<p>&hellip;also its cute.</p>
<h3 id="oook-go-on-then">Oook, go on then&hellip;</h3>
<p>These little printers are available on the usual online retailers, like <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Wireless-Bluetooth-Printers-Learning-Compatible/dp/B09MCNVRJD/ref=sr_1_4?crid=32XFNY7KOPHZC&amp;keywords=cat+printer&amp;qid=1650708084&amp;s=computers&amp;sprefix=cat+printer%2Ccomputers%2C48&amp;sr=1-4">Amazon</a> and <a href="https://www.aliexpress.com/item/1005003341930695.html?spm=a2g0o.productlist.0.0.2e9f6430zpLBgL&amp;algo_pvid=cb9834a6-5a6c-4359-ac4a-105c7c4376f3&amp;algo_exp_id=cb9834a6-5a6c-4359-ac4a-105c7c4376f3-0&amp;pdp_ext_f=%7B%22sku_id%22%3A%2212000027021364344%22%7D&amp;pdp_pi=31.03%3B10.91%3B-1%3B-1%40salePrice%3BGBP%3Bsearch-mainSearch">AliExpress</a> for ~£30. There are also other, non animal based versions too.</p>
<p>They are intended to be used with a mobile application called &ldquo;<a href="https://apps.apple.com/gb/app/iprint/id1542944105">iPrint</a>&rdquo; in order to print text or images.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/img_0463.PNG" alt=""  />
</p>
<p>But, what if you want to use your cat printer in another way? With your computer or some other device? Well, thanks to other hackers there are plenty of options out there;</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>There is a <a href="https://hackaday.com/2021/09/21/mini-wireless-thermal-printers-get-arduino-library-and-macos-app/">hackaday</a> article here that covers both <a href="https://github.com/bitbank2/Thermal_Printer">Arduino</a> and <a href="https://github.com/bitbank2/Print2BLE">macOS</a> options by <a href="https://github.com/bitbank2">Larry Bank</a>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If CircutPython is more your jam, you can check out this tutorial on Adafruit <a href="https://learn.adafruit.com/ble-thermal-cat-printer-with-circuitpython">here</a> by <a href="https://learn.adafruit.com/users/jepler">Jeff Epler</a>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Or, if you&rsquo;re more into regular python, or rust there is a good list of projects <a href="https://github.com/JJJollyjim/catprinter">here</a>.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>But, like any hacker knows, the fact there is already a way to do something isn&rsquo;t a good enough reason not to do it yourself! So that is what I did!</p>
<p>But first, let&rsquo;s talk a little about the&hellip;</p>
<h3 id="hardware">Hardware</h3>
<p>The hardware is pretty well documented already, a good example is the <a href="https://werwolv.net/blog/cat_printer">writeup</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/WerWolv">WerWolv</a>.</p>
<p>But, to give some context here is a quick overview;</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a thermal printer and uses 57mm paper, similar to what you&rsquo;d find in card machines and the like. It can fit approx 40mm diameter rolls of paper.</p>
<p>The print resolution is 384px wide (203dpi), being a thermal printer, it can only print in monochrome (1bit / black and white)</p>
<p>The brains of the operation is a JL MCU that there is vanishingly little documentation for, and the printer communicates with other devices via Bluetooth Low Energy (BLE).</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s powered by an internal lithium battery and is charged via micro-usb.</p>
<p>And the most important feature, it has little ears and a cute face.</p>
<p>So with that in mind, on to the&hellip;</p>
<h3 id="software">Software</h3>
<p>I decided to build my version of cat printer goodness in NodeJS, which I&rsquo;ve called <code>printkitty.js</code>, imaginative, I know. You can check it out on <a href="https://github.com/sophienyaa/printkitty.js">GitHub here</a></p>
<p>I chose NodeJS mostly because it&rsquo;s what I am comfortable with. This, as it turns out, may not have been the best decision&hellip; due to reasons I&rsquo;ll get in to later.</p>
<p>The printer has no &lsquo;pure&rsquo; text mode or inbuilt fonts. It simply prints everything as an image. So with that in mind, my initial goal was simply to be able to send images to the printer.</p>
<h4 id="bluetooth-low-energy">Bluetooth Low Energy</h4>
<p>To do this, the first thing I needed was a BLE library. I settled on <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/@abandonware/noble">noble</a>, as it seemed easy enough to work with, and there aren&rsquo;t a lot of other choices for Node.</p>
<p>I then came across <a href="https://github.com/JJJollyjim/catprinter">this repository</a> from <a href="https://twitter.com/JJJollyjim">JJJollyjim</a> that collects a bunch of cat printer projects, and then a <a href="https://github.com/JJJollyjim/catprinter/blob/f5322f7d728ed491218d788f0eff6cad7e11ab3f/COMMANDS.md">document</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/bad_opcode">bad_opcode</a> that had nice and clear documentation of the protocol used.</p>
<p>Once I was able to connect to the printer with noble, I scanned for characteristics and found quite a few&hellip; <code>AE01,AE02,AE03,AE04,AE05,AE10</code>. with <code>AE01</code> being write only, and <code>AE10</code> being read/write, and <code>AE02</code> and <code>AE04</code> being for notifications.</p>
<p>I initially tried the <code>AE10</code> read/write characteristic, but had no luck making the printer do anything. I then tried <code>AE01</code> and wrote the bytes for a &rsquo;eject paper&rsquo;, and much to my excitement, paper came out of the printer.</p>
<p>I then tried to get info, while listening to <code>AE02</code> and I did indeed receive some data on that characteristic. With the knowledge that this was likely to work&hellip;</p>
<h4 id="lets-try-and-make-it-print-something">Let&rsquo;s try and make it print something</h4>
<p>I had read that the printer essentially took an array of bits to construct an image, 1 for black (e.g activate the printhead) and 0 for white. (e.g dont)</p>
<p>This is where my choice of NodeJS started to become less than ideal. JavaScript is not exactly the most low level language, and working with individual bits isn&rsquo;t particularly ergonomic, compared to say C/C++ (which I am somewhat used to in playing with microcontrollers).</p>
<p>With that said, I was able to construct bit strings (e.g <code>&quot;11111111&quot;</code>) and parse those in to integers (e.g <code>255</code> / <code>0xFF</code>). That has proven to be good enough. So I &lsquo;drew&rsquo; a square in bits, parsed it to bytes and constructed an array of with one <code>Buffer</code> for each like, and each buffer.</p>
<p>I sent the square to the printer, and it printed, but didn&rsquo;t advance as it did so. So I threw a call to feed the paper by one step each iteration. I then had a square, but the sides of it were on the inside, so It looked more like an <code>I</code>. I then went back and re-read the <a href="https://github.com/JJJollyjim/catprinter/blob/f5322f7d728ed491218d788f0eff6cad7e11ab3f/COMMANDS.md">document</a> and realised I missed this <em>very</em> important bit under the print section&hellip; &ldquo;with each byte packed with the least significant bit first.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The easiest / laziest way to resolve this was simply to reverse the bit strings and then parse that into bytes. There is probably a better way to do this, bit it works well enough for now.</p>
<p>After doing that, I got my square! Now on to the next challenge, trying to print something meaningful (&hellip;and by that, I mean a picture of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grumpy_Cat">grumpy cat)</a>.</p>
<h4 id="parsing-images-in-nodejs">Parsing images in NodeJS</h4>
<p>Turns out this was another sucky thing about using NodeJS, there aren&rsquo;t a huge amount of image processing libraries. I settled on <a href="https://sharp.pixelplumbing.com/">sharp</a> and while it is very performant and easy to use, there aren&rsquo;t a lot of options for producing pure monochrome images. I tried using its inbuilt dithering but always ended up with an image that was grey and white, not black and white.</p>
<p>I then came across <a href="https://twitter.com/noopkat">noopkat&rsquo;s</a> <a href="https://github.com/noopkat/floyd-steinberg">floyd-steinberg</a> package, that was able to produce the results I was after.</p>
<p>After pluming it and sharp together, I was able to produce dithered, monochrome images from a wide range of input image formats. There is definitely better ways to do this, so any suggestions are welcome!</p>
<h4 id="building-a-bitmap">Building a bitmap</h4>
<p>Now that I had monochrome images, I needed to turn those into 1bpp bitmaps that the printer could understand. If you&rsquo;ve ever worked with small monochrome displays and microcontrollers this should be sort familiar.</p>
<p>As said above, the format is 1 bit per pixel, with 0 for white and 1 for black, grouped in to bytes with the least significant bit first. As the print area is 348px wide, this means 48 bytes of data per line.</p>
<p>I learnt here, that if you provide less than 48 bytes per line, the printer will <strong>not</strong> automatically advance when given the next line.</p>
<p>The final data structure for my bitmap was an array of <code>Buffer</code> objects, with each one being 48 bytes. When initialised they are filled with 0&rsquo;s so if the image is less than 348px wide, it will be padded with 0&rsquo;s.</p>
<p>Now that I had all this, I was able to start..</p>
<h4 id="printing-actual-images">Printing actual images</h4>
<p>I started trying to feed data to the printer, following the same set of commands that existing code did;</p>
<ol>
<li>Set the quality, I&rsquo;ve set it to &lsquo;3&rsquo; and this seems to work fine</li>
<li>Send the first magic &rsquo;lattice&rsquo; command</li>
<li>Set the print &rsquo;energy&rsquo; to medium</li>
<li>Set the drawing mode (it has a &rsquo;text&rsquo; mode, to spite not having a way to print text)</li>
<li>Setting the feed speed to <code>0x23</code>, as seems to be done in the other solutions</li>
<li>Sending the print data</li>
<li>Feeding the paper for 120 steps</li>
<li>Doing the last &rsquo;lattice&rsquo; command</li>
</ol>
<p>This order of operations was discovered by during the reverse engineering of the &ldquo;iPrint&rdquo; app done by <a href="https://werwolv.net/blog/cat_printer">WerWolv</a>.</p>
<p>However, each time I tried, I&rsquo;d only get a few lines of the print out before it would stop. This is because I had neglected to put a delay between each line of the print data.</p>
<p>As others had discovered and documented, if you don&rsquo;t do this, the printer will get overwhelmed and stop printing.</p>
<p>Herein lies yet another issue with JavaScript. There is no native <code>delay()</code> or <code>sleep()</code> functionality. Annoying as it is, it does makes sense when you understand the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8aGhZQkoFbQ">JS event loop</a>.</p>
<p>However, for this purpose it is not difficult hack one in and allow the code to pause for 10ms between sending commands to the printer. This solved the the issue and I was finally able to print images successfully!</p>
<p>Now simply by running <code>printkitty --image grumpy.png</code> I was able to get this:</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>Printing images is cool and all, but&hellip;</p>
<h4 id="what-about-text">What about text?</h4>
<p>Because our little cat printer can <em>only</em> do images, if we want to print text we need to find a way to turn our text into an image!</p>
<p>This was where using sharp turned out to be a good decision. It is incredibly easy to build an SVG (as after all SVGs are markup very similar to HTML) that contains the text you want to print, and then turn that in to an image and print it in the same way as you do any other.</p>
<p>I found a very cool <a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/how-to-process-images-in-node-js-with-sharp">article</a> from DigitalOcean about how to use sharp for more general image processing, but it was here I found the idea of simply constructing a SVG, turning it in to an image and processing it.</p>
<p>One thing to note here, is I skip the dithering process as the generated text is always going to be monochrome. The other fun part about doing it this way, is it makes it very easy to pass in font and font size choices for our printed text.</p>
<p>This code I&rsquo;ve written to handle text is pretty rudimentary, and I&rsquo;ve not yet added a way to scale the height of the image with the text, but I can fix that in later releases.</p>
<p>All of this culminated in being able to run <code>printkitty --text &quot;~nyaa&quot; --font &quot;Comic Sans MS&quot; --size 100</code> and getting this:</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>So I can print images, and even text now, but to do so I need to run them through my app. What if I wanted to be able to <em>just print</em> from any application like you can with any other <em>boring, non-cat printer</em>?</p>
<h4 id="enter-ipp-internet-printing-protocol">Enter, IPP (Internet Printing Protocol)</h4>
<p>IPP is a standard that has been around for some time, with the idea being that you can print documents over a network (or, like, the internet) to any printer without pesky things like drivers or software.</p>
<p>My boring, <em>non-cat</em> Samsung laser printer supports it, as do basically any modern network enabled printer. What I didn&rsquo;t realise is how <em>simple</em> a protocol it is</p>
<p>I found <a href="https://github.com/watson/ipp-printer">this package</a> from <a href="https://twitter.com/wa7son">watson</a> that implemented a basic IPP server in node and watched his <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=58Ti8w1yX2w">accompanying talk</a> on the protocol and how he did it. It also supports niceties like Bonjour/zeroconf making actually adding your cat printer to your system a snap.</p>
<p>The package listens for print jobs and then outputs them to your local filesystem as postscript files. This was great, but sadly sharp doesn&rsquo;t support these.</p>
<p>I was again let down by NodeJS when I couldn&rsquo;t find any native libraries to handle converting postscript to an image (e.g PNG) that I could easily process.</p>
<p>I did however find wrappers around <a href="https://www.ghostscript.com/">ghostscript</a>, which can perform this task. But this would mean a dependancy on <code>gs</code> being installed. I wanted to avoid this, but sadly I could not find any other viable options.</p>
<p>Ultimately, I decided to skip using a wrapper and simply call <code>gs</code> from within my code by using Node&rsquo;s <code>child_process</code> package. This is a bit hack-y but it works well enough for this application.</p>
<p>So with all that in place, I was able to generate a PNG image, from the received postscript print data and pass that into my existing code.</p>
<p>All of this means, I could simply run <code>printkitty --ipp</code> and I was able to use my cat printer from any application!</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>There is still more to do, like generally improve the code and try and hack in AirPrint support, but that will have to wait for a future post.</p>
<p>Ok, so what was the point of all this?</p>
<h3 id="conclusion-and-thanks">Conclusion and thanks</h3>
<p>Well&hellip; the point of this&hellip; was&hellip; <em>just to do it.</em></p>
<p>To elaborate on that, it was to learn more about my little cat-faced, thermal printing, friend by experimenting on it.</p>
<p>In these experiments, along with learning about the hardware itself,  I learnt more about Node and JavaScript in general. I also learnt a little about how IPP worked, something I&rsquo;d used plenty but never really thought about. I also got a handful of likes and hopefully also made some smile on twitter.</p>
<p>The friend who inspired me to get one in the first place conducted her own set of cat printer experimentation, going even further by setting up things like a <a href="https://twitter.com/xssfox/status/1469595519773122566">telegram bot</a> and printing images from <a href="https://twitter.com/xssfox/status/1418727717135028227">SSTV</a>, which are worth checking out.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;ve got your own cat printer, or been inspired to get one by this post, please give <a href="https://github.com/sophienyaa/printkitty.js">printkitty.js</a> a try, I&rsquo;d love to hear your feedback&hellip; and if you go on to experiment yourself I&rsquo;d absolutely love to see your car printer projects!</p>
<p>Finally, I&rsquo;d like to say thanks to everyone who&rsquo;s work I&rsquo;ve referenced in this post, as what they&rsquo;ve done has enabled my experimentation here.</p>
 ]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yet another Raspberry Pi Cyberdeck</title>
      <link>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2021-01-16-yet-another-raspberry-pi-cyberdeck/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 17:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>me@sophi.ee (Sophie 🌸)</author>
      <guid>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2021-01-16-yet-another-raspberry-pi-cyberdeck/</guid>
      <description>If you are a regular reader of blogs like hackaday, then you will have noticed in recent years that &amp;lsquo;cyberdecks&amp;rsquo; have become quite popular.
Most of these are essentially custom designed/built laptops based around various SBCs, with the Rapsberry Pi being a popular choice. Some of them use Intel NUCs or other PC hardware, some even feature head mounted displays!
They generally have a retro-futuristic, hand-built, utilitarian aesthetic. Cyberdecks often feature in cyberpunk books, movies, video games, etc.</description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[ <p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/dmesg.jpg" alt="Header Image"  />
</p>
<p>If you are a regular reader of blogs like <a href="https://hackaday.com/" title="hackaday">hackaday</a>, then you will have noticed in recent years that &lsquo;cyberdecks&rsquo; have become quite popular.</p>
<p>Most of these are essentially custom designed/built laptops based around various SBCs, with the <a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/">Rapsberry Pi</a> being a popular choice. Some of them use <a href="https://www.intel.co.uk/content/www/uk/en/products/boards-kits/nuc.html">Intel NUCs</a> or other PC hardware, some even feature head mounted displays!</p>
<p>They generally have a retro-futuristic, hand-built, utilitarian aesthetic. Cyberdecks often feature in cyberpunk books, movies, video games, etc.</p>
<h2 id="first-attempts">First Attempts</h2>
<p>I love the design of these, and over the last year or so I have experimented with the idea of building my own. I have even done a few prototypes or builds that I never finished or discarded for some reason. They were all based largely around the same hardware.</p>
<p>My first go was a laser-cut acrylic design, this was before I purchased a 3D printer. I used the laser cutter at my local <a href="https://bristol.hackspace.org.uk/" title="hackspace">hackspace</a>.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/img_1409.jpg" alt="First Attempt"  />
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It was a thing, it worked but I didn&rsquo;t like the design or assembly.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It was based around a Raspberry Pi 4, 7&quot; LCD touchscreen and a &lsquo;AK33&rsquo; mechanical keyboard.</p>
<p>I abandoned this design pretty early on, it was a pain to put together and I wasn&rsquo;t happy with how it looked.</p>
<p>A while later, I bought a 3d printer (<a href="https://creality3d.shop/products/creality3d-ender-3-pro-high-precision-3d-printer">Ender 3 Pro</a>) and set about designing my next attempt.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/img_1868.jpg" alt="Second Attempt"  />
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This one was much better, but I still wasn&rsquo;t happy.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This one used the same hardware, and I was sort-of happy with it, but I could never get the keyboard to sit right and it was a pain to print, so I gave up on this design.</p>
<h2 id="current-attempt">Current &lsquo;Attempt&rsquo;</h2>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/dmesg.jpg" alt="Curent Attempt"  />
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Here it is, in all its glory!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Over the Christmas break, inspired by 100+ hours of Cyberpunk 2077 (Which, I loved, to spite its flaws) I thought I&rsquo;d have another go at this whole cyberdeck thing.</p>
<p>My 3D modeling skills are <em>slightly</em> better than when I made the first attempt (though still very poor) so I hoped I&rsquo;d have more success.</p>
<p>I wanted my cyberdeck to have certain features/qualities;</p>
<ol>
<li>It had to be portable, and able to run from a battery.</li>
<li>I wanted to include an SDR in it, so it could be used as a portable listening station</li>
<li>I wanted to use the same AK33 keyboard I had from the previous attempts</li>
<li>I wanted it to be &lsquo;clean&rsquo;&hellip; e.g no cables hanging out, etc.</li>
<li>I wanted it to be easy to put together.</li>
</ol>
<p>With those goals in mind, I fired up <a href="https://www.autodesk.co.uk/products/fusion-360/overview">Fusion360</a>, a piece of software with which I have a love hate relationship and set to work.</p>
<h3 id="design">Design</h3>
<p>I went with largely the same aesthetic as the first 3D printed attempt. Sort of inspired by the Amiga 600 or Commodore 64C and other similar machines, but with a screen on top.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/amiga_600.jpg" alt="An Amiga 600"  />
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If you squint hard, it almost looks like one! (Image from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amiga_600">Wikipedia</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>With the design somewhat laid out in my head, I started drawing. I split the machine in to 4 main sections, so as to fit on my printers bed.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/cyberdeck-mode.png" alt="3D Models of the Design"  />
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>3D Models of the major components</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The two rear sections contain most of the hardware, and are bolted together. On top go two slotted &rsquo;lids&rsquo; with the uprights for the display hinges.</p>
<p>The two front sections attach with tabs that slide in to the rear sections. They are also bolted in the middle.</p>
<p>The front sections only contain standoffs for they keyboard, but could easily hold additional hardware (there&rsquo;s a bit of room underneath, especially towards the back.</p>
<p>You will notice the evenly-spaced holes in the bottom of the device. My idea was here that it would make it easy to add and remove hardware. Each device, like the Pi, USB Hub, etc is on a separate carrier that is bolted to the bottom of the board.</p>
<p>If you want to build your own, but are using slightly different hardware to me, all you need to do is design carriers for it, rather than changing the whole case.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/pi-holder-2.jpg" alt="Pi Carrier"  />
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Quicker than re-printing the whole section!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It also made it much easier, as if I made a mistake on the hole spacing for the RPi, I only needed to re-print the carrier, not the whole device!</p>
<p>With all that in mind, let&rsquo;s turn to the actual hardware in the cyberdeck.</p>
<h3 id="hardware">Hardware</h3>
<p>I am using largely the same hardware from my first attempts, but let&rsquo;s look at it in a little more detail.</p>
<p>The SBC is a Raspberry Pi 4, 4Gb model. It currently has a 16Gb SD card, but I will be swapping that for a larger one.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/pi-cabling.jpg" alt="RPi and USB Hub"  />
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The Pi next to the USB Hub</p>
</blockquote>
<p>On top of that, is a UPSPack V3. This is a cheap but feature rich UPS board for Raspberry Pi&rsquo;s. It can do 5V, 3A output, report data to the Pi via serial (such as charge status) and shutdown the Pi gracefully before the battery runs out.</p>
<p>It handles charging via USB-C and has a pair of external (unused in my design) USB ports for powering other devices. I also soldered wires for an external switch that is mounted in the back panel of the cyberdeck.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/pi-ups.jpg" alt="UPS Board"  />
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Stacked neatly on top of each other</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Next to the Pi is an &lsquo;internal&rsquo; USB hub, its designed for use in PCs for running things like RGB and Fan Controllers, but it was perfect for my application. It is a 4 port hub with standard USB headers like you&rsquo;d find in any PC.</p>
<p><em>Update: I tested the battery life by running Chrome with a YouTube video playing and logging the uptime every 2s to a file. The result was 3h 40m of runtime.</em></p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/usb-hub.jpg" alt="USB Hub"  />
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Nestled between the Pi and the battery</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I attached a USB plug to its cable, which is plugged into the bottom USB2 port on the Pi, this whole mess is covered by a plate. I think I might change this design by soldering wires to the underside of the Pi and then just blanking the usb port.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/usb-side.jpg" alt="USB Ports"  />
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Not the most elegant, but it works</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Connected to this hub is they keyboard, display and SDR. I made custom mini and micro USB to header cables to connect the various peripherals.</p>
<p>The SDR is a cheap RTL-SDR board I got from amazon, it has two RF inputs and is in a neat metal case to keep it isolated from other devices. It connects via mini USB to the internal hub</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/sdr-side.jpg" alt="SDR Side"  />
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I did have a plate for this side, but it made using the RF connectors a pain</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The keyboard is the same as used in previous attempts. It has &lsquo;RGB&rsquo; lighting (not customisable sadly&hellip; I did have one that was but I managed to fry it 😢).</p>
<p>The RGB is actually kind of a pain, as it draws a lot of power and causes weirdness when the cyberdeck is booted without being plugged in to mains. I am likely to disable it (read: cut the power traces for it 😈) in future.</p>
<p>It is a fairly basic &lsquo;cheap&rsquo; mechanical keyboard, but its actually not too bad to type on and its fits the aesthetic I was going for. It connects via mini-USB to the internal hub.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/keyboard.jpg" alt="Keyboard"  />
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The keyboard in all its glory, and the official RPi mouse!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Finally, the display is a 7&quot; IPS LCD. It has a resolution of 1024x600 and includes capacitive touch. It connects to the Pi via HDMI and the power and touchscreen via a micro USB cable. The cable is also spliced in to the UPSs&rsquo; 5v output as the screen draws a lot of current.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/display-mounted.jpg" alt="Display Mounted"  />
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The display mounted on the cyberdeck</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The display is connected via a &lsquo;custom HDMI cable kit&rsquo; from The Pi Hut. It allows you to mix and match connectors for HDMI and uses a flex flat cable to go between them, quite useful for things like this.</p>
<p>There is a panel on the back of the unit to cover the connections, but leaving open the power input (on the UPS Board) and the 3.5mm audio jack</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/rear-port.jpg" alt="Rear Panel"  />
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You can still access the ports you need to</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That&rsquo;s pretty much it for the hardware. It&rsquo;s a standard Raspberry Pi 4. There are 2x USB3 ports accessable, 1x USB2 and 1x Gigabit Ethernet.</p>
<h3 id="bill-of-materials">Bill Of Materials</h3>
<p>Below is a pretty much complete list of the parts used and where I got them from. Prices are as at the time I purchased. You can likely find things cheaper on sites like Aliexpress, or you can even swap things out for other hardware.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Device</th>
<th>Description</th>
<th>Cost/Vendor</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Raspberry Pi 4</td>
<td>4Gb Model</td>
<td>£54 <a href="https://shop.pimoroni.com/products/raspberry-pi-4?variant=29157087445075">Pimoroni</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>UPSPack V3</td>
<td>UPS &amp; Battery</td>
<td>£25.99 <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B0719Q5M9X">Amazon</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>USB Hub</td>
<td>Internal USB Hub</td>
<td>£7.59 <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B075XR1Q751">Amazon</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AK33</td>
<td>Mechanical Keyboard</td>
<td>£31.99 <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B07XFR338G">Amazon</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SDR</td>
<td>KKMoon RTL-SDR</td>
<td>£32.99 <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B0716CB1PM">Amazon</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Display</td>
<td>7&quot; HDMI IPS Touchscreen</td>
<td>£28.05 <a href="https://www.aliexpress.com/item/4000829569543.html">Aliexpress</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>USB Cable</td>
<td>2x 50cm Mini-USB Cables</td>
<td>£2.99 ea <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B00DY2NAYE/">Amazon</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>USB Cable</td>
<td>1x Right angle micro-USB Cables</td>
<td>£3.99 <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/StarTech-com-Micro-USB-Cable-Right-Angled-Connectors-Black/dp/B012S11KV6/ref=sr_1_3?dchild=1&amp;keywords=right+angle+micro+usb&amp;qid=1610904731&amp;s=electronics&amp;sr=1-3">Amazon</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HDMI Connector</td>
<td>Up angle micro HDMI Connector</td>
<td>£6 <a href="https://thepihut.com/products/diy-hdmi-cable-parts-right-angle-r-bend-micro-hdmi-plug">The Pi Hut</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HDMI Connector</td>
<td>Standard HDMI Connector</td>
<td>£6 <a href="https://thepihut.com/products/diy-hdmi-cable-parts-straight-hdmi-plug-adapter">The Pi Hut</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HDMI Cable</td>
<td>50cm Flex Cable</td>
<td>£3 <a href="https://thepihut.com/products/diy-usb-or-hdmi-cable-parts-50-cm-ribbon-cable">The Pi Hut</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dupont Connectors</td>
<td>1550 pcs kit + Crimp Tool</td>
<td>£20.99 <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B078K9DT69/">Amazon</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Nuts &amp; Bolts</td>
<td>440 pcs kit</td>
<td>£15.99 <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B075CKYJF6">Amazon</a></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h3 id="software">Software</h3>
<p>Right now, the deck is simply running Raspbian, with a few little tweaks to make things like the UPS and Display work correctly.</p>
<p>I might try out other distributions in the future, such as Kali Linux, but for now Raspbian is fine!</p>
<p>For a laugh, I installed steam link and had a go at playing Cyberpunk2077 on my cyberdeck. It worked surprisingly well, but I think I&rsquo;d rather my 32&quot; 1440p gaming monitor over a 7&quot; 600p display running at 30Hz</p>
<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aXAGUp6Lsp0" title="Cyberpunk on a Cyberdeck">
<img class="enclosure" src="http://img.youtube.com/vi/aXAGUp6Lsp0/0.jpg" alt="Cyberpunk on Cyberdeck"  />
</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Click the thumbnail to see the video</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Display</strong></p>
<p>The display &lsquo;works&rsquo; out of the box as its a simple HDMI display, and the touch drivers are included in Raspbian, so the only thing I needed to do was set some config to have it run at its native resolution. I used the guide from Adafruit <a href="">here</a>, but the TL;DR is:</p>
<p>add the below lines to <code>/boot/config.txt</code> and reboot.</p>
<pre><code>hdmi_group=2
hdmi_mode=1
hdmi_mode=87
hdmi_cvt=1024 600 60 3 0 0 0
</code></pre>
<p><strong>UPS</strong></p>
<p>The UPS also &lsquo;works&rsquo; but requires some config changes if you want to be able to see the data over serial, or have the Pi shutdown automatically. They are details in the documentation <a href="https://github.com/rcdrones/UPSPACK_V3/blob/master/README_en.md#Software-Drivers" title="here">here</a>.</p>
<p>You will need to download the scripts they provide if you want a nice way to view the UPS details, but if like me you just need to get the data flowing (I plan to build my own software to show battery status) then add the below to your <code>/boot/config.txt</code> and reboot.</p>
<pre><code>enable_uart=1
dtoverlay=disable-bt
</code></pre>
<p>Once you&rsquo;ve done that, you&rsquo;ll be able to see the data on <code>/dev/ttyAMA0</code> at 9600baud.</p>
<h3 id="inspiration-and-why-would-i-want-to-do-this">Inspiration, and why would I want to do this?</h3>
<p>Like a lot of hardware projects, its better to ask&hellip; why not?</p>
<p>There are plenty of practical reasons you might want to build your own cyberdeck&hellip; maybe you want something portable for &lsquo;hacking in the field&rsquo;, something that contains the exact hardware you need for that&hellip; such as a built in SDR like my deck has.</p>
<p>But largely, at least for me, I built one because I <em>wanted</em> to. The first deck I remember seeing that made me think about building my own was the <a href="https://back7.co/home/raspberry-pi-recovery-kit">&lsquo;Off-Grid cyberdeck&rsquo;</a> by back7. I saw it browsing hackday a few years ago and loved the idea of a portable pi, with custom hardware (e.g the GPIO ports and network switch in back7&rsquo;s deck.</p>
<p>There was also decks like <a href="https://cyberdeck.cafe/mix/virtuscope">&lsquo;The Virtuscope&rsquo;</a> and this awesome <a href="https://imgur.com/a/h2kR0Gs">NUC based deck</a>. Sites like they <a href="https://cyberdeck.cafe/">cyberdeck cafe</a> and the <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/cyberDeck">cyberdeck subreddit</a> are full of inspiring builds.</p>
<p>More generally, the whole &lsquo;cyberpunk&rsquo; / &lsquo;retrowave&rsquo; / &lsquo;retro-future&rsquo; aesthetic is something that appeales to me.</p>
<p>So will I used this deck for anything? Maybe, maybe not. Did I enjoy building it? Certainly, and that&rsquo;s really all that matters.</p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>This current iteration of my cyberdeck is one I am finally &lsquo;happy&rsquo; with. It&rsquo;s definitely not perfect, and no doubt I will change and improve the design in the future. But I have enjoyed building it, and hopefully given you some inspiration to build one yourself.</p>
<p>If you want to build your own, the STL files are available on thingiverse <a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:4726880/files">here</a>, and you can use the above table for the hardware you&rsquo;ll need.</p>
<p>If you can think of ways to improve my design, or this has inspired you to create your own I&rsquo;d love to hear about them, you can send me a tweet <a href="https://twitter.com/mickwheelz_">@mickwheelz_</a>!</p>
 ]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microservices inside Salesforce With Platform Events and Change Data Capture, Part Two</title>
      <link>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2020-12-27-microservices-inside-salesforce-with-platform-events-and-change-data-capture-part-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>me@sophi.ee (Sophie 🌸)</author>
      <guid>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2020-12-27-microservices-inside-salesforce-with-platform-events-and-change-data-capture-part-two/</guid>
      <description>Now that the holidays are over, its time for Part Two! Haven&amp;rsquo;t read part one yet? Check it out and then come back, don&amp;rsquo;t worry, I&amp;rsquo;ll wait for you.
⌚️
Finished? Great, let&amp;rsquo;s go!
How does this work on Salesforce? As we discussed in part one, we can take advantage of the Salesforce enterprise messaging platform to build &amp;lsquo;microservices&amp;rsquo; in Salesforce.
Before we go any further, these microservices are a little different from traditional ones.</description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[ <p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/23b9a76b8b2a24bf3937cd648179c24f_badge.png" alt="Header Image"  />
</p>
<p>Now that the holidays are over, its time for Part Two! Haven&rsquo;t read <a href="https://mickwheelz.net/salesforce/microservices/2020/12/12/microservices-on-salesforce.html" title="part one">part one</a> yet? Check it out and then come back, don&rsquo;t worry, I&rsquo;ll wait for you.</p>
<p>⌚️</p>
<p>Finished? Great, let&rsquo;s go!</p>
<h3 id="how-does-this-work-on-salesforce">How does this work on Salesforce?</h3>
<p>As we discussed in part one, we can take advantage of the Salesforce enterprise messaging platform to build &lsquo;microservices&rsquo; in Salesforce.</p>
<p>Before we go any further, these microservices are a little different from traditional ones. As we know, Salesforce provides a platform as a Service. This includes everything we need, including the database, the runtime, the language, etc. As we know, we can <em>only</em> use the tools provided by the platform. We can&rsquo;t just deploy some random java to our salesforce org (yet&hellip; 😉) so we must write our on-platform services in Apex* and we use the database we are given*</p>
<p>*(yes there are other languages/databases (e.g JS in Aura/LWC and External Objects&hellip; but that&rsquo;s out of the scope of this post!)</p>
<p>So in reality, our services are discrete &lsquo;chunks&rsquo; of Apex that don&rsquo;t have dependancies on other code, or potentially even objects in Salesforce (aside from the Platform Event definition they use).</p>
<p>We still get most of the same advantages as traditional microservices. We can however, have microservices in our Application that are <em>outside</em> of salesforce, and these can behave as traditional microservices, with their own language, database, runtime, etc. We will cover these too!</p>
<p>So let&rsquo;s take a look at how we do this&hellip;</p>
<h3 id="on-platform">On Platform</h3>
<p>Let&rsquo;s think about the example from part one. We have a simple billing system that uses Opportunities and Opportunity Line Items. When an Opportunity is closed/won, we want a PDF invoice (with the line items listed on it) generated and attached to the Opportunity.</p>
<p>Using the &lsquo;old&rsquo; way, you might have a trigger on the opportunity that uses VisualForce to generate the PDF and attach it to the Opportunity. This runs on synchronously on save and you may eventually run into limit issues with this approach.</p>
<p>So how do we do it using microservices? Well let&rsquo;s take a look at the below diagram</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/image12.png" alt=""  />
</p>
<p>If you want to see the example code for this approach, you can check out the repo <a href="https://github.com/mickwheelz/DF2019-Invoicing-Salesforce" title="here">here</a> and it is referenced below.</p>
<p>You can see here we have three &lsquo;services&rsquo;;</p>
<ol>
<li>The Apex trigger <code>OpportunityChangeEventTrigger</code>, is on the Opportunity Change Data (CDC) event, so it isn&rsquo;t run synchronously. It simply it calls the   <code>OpportunityChangeEventService</code> class to fires the Invoice Request Platform Event (PE) that contains the information needed to generate the Invoice. This approach is taken to decouple the next service from the Opportunity.</li>
<li>The Invoice generation service. This listens for the Invoice Request PE in the <code>GenerateInvoicePDFTrigger</code>, then calls the <code>InvoicePDFService</code> and it uses VisualForce (<code>InvoicePDF</code> / <code>InvoicePDFController</code>) to generate a PDF invoice from the information contained in the event. It knows nothing about the original opportunity (this is important!) When it is finished it simply fires a &lsquo;Invoice Response&rsquo; PE. It ONLY generates PDFs, nothing else.</li>
<li>Finally, we have <code>InvoicePDFTrigger</code> that listens for the Invoice Response PE and then calls the <code>InvoicePDFService</code> so that it can insert an attachment record. It doesn&rsquo;t know or care where the PDF actually came from.</li>
</ol>
<p>None of these services have any hard dependencies on each other. They do their small individual jobs and that is it. They also all run asynchronously so the user doesn&rsquo;t need to sit and wait for them to complete for their record to be saved.</p>
<p>Want to see how this looks under the hood? Well you can check out the code here</p>
<p>So what happens when our little VisualForce PDF generator service stops scaling or is otherwise unfit for purpose? Well, we simply replace it with something&hellip;</p>
<h3 id="off-platform">Off Platform</h3>
<p>We&rsquo;ve decided we are going to use a small service running on Heroku to generate our PDFs now, so we&rsquo;ve written something in NodeJS and deployed it. Let&rsquo;s take a look at how we switch to using this now.</p>
<p>If you want to take a look at the code for the Heroku service, you can see it <a href="https://github.com/mickwheelz/DF2019-Invoicing-Heroku" title="here">here</a>, It is referenced below.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/image11.png" alt=""  />
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You can see we again have three services, and the first and third have not changed. The code is identical. We have ONLY replaced the middle service.</p>
<p>The NodeJS is very simple, in <code>index.js</code> the <code>begin()</code> function it logs in to Salesforce (to access the event bus) and then begins listening for Invoice Request PEs. If it receives  one, it calls <code>processGenerateInvoicePDFEvent()</code> which uses <a href="https://pdfkit.org/" title="PDFKit">PDFKit</a> to generate the invoice PDF, this is handled in <code>generateInvoice.js</code></p>
<p>When it is finished generating the PDF, <code>fireInvoicePDFEvent</code> is called to fire the Invoice Response PE for to be picked up by our attachment service inside salesforce.</p>
<p>To handle the Salesforce requests, we are using the excellent <a href="https://jsforce.github.io/" title="JSForce">JSForce</a> library.</p>
<p>Now that we have our little PDF service running, I bet you are wondering how we switch to using it.</p>
<p>We disable <code>GenerateInvoicePDFTrigger</code> &hellip; that&rsquo;s it. Seriously.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/screenshot-2020-12-27-at-11-57-43.png" alt=""  />
</p>
<p>If we want to switch back, all we need to do is shut down our Heroku service and switch the trigger back on. Simples!</p>
<p>Of course, in the real world we would likely remove the trigger from production once we had finished migrating to the new service, but you can see how simple it is with this approach.</p>
<p>Now that we&rsquo;ve see how we can create microservices on and off platform, and swap them at will we should&hellip;</p>
<h3 id="wrap-up">Wrap Up</h3>
<p>The event driven paradigm is a very flexible one and allows things to change without the usual level of friction. It can speed up development, and allow teams to work in parallel. It can even speed up the end user experience, as everything is done async. It is an excellent option for large and complex Applications, but it is not a silver bullet.</p>
<p>It does introduce more &lsquo;moving parts&rsquo;, for smaller, simpler applications this may not be worth it. It is also worth considering the <a href="https://developer.salesforce.com/docs/atlas.en-us.platform_events.meta/platform_events/platform_events_api_considerations.htm">limits of platform events</a>, for very large volumes you may need to move to a different event bus, such as <a href="https://kafka.apache.org/intro">Apache Kafka</a>. Salesforce cannot natively talk to Kafka, but you can use middleware like MuleSoft or you can build your own bespoke services to do so (a topic for a future post perhaps&hellip; 🤔)</p>
<p>You should <strong>always</strong> take time to consider what is the right approach for what you are building, both now and in the future. However I hope this post has informed and inspired you to think about how you could use this architecture in Salesforce!</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;ve got any questions or comments, please send me a tweet <a href="https://twitter.com/mickwheelz_">@mickwheelz_</a></p>
 ]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microservices inside Salesforce With Platform Events and Change Data Capture, Part One.</title>
      <link>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2020-12-12-microservices-on-salesforce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>me@sophi.ee (Sophie 🌸)</author>
      <guid>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2020-12-12-microservices-on-salesforce/</guid>
      <description>Normally, when I do a talk at Dreamforce, or another conference, I write a follow up blog post covering the same content. But the end of 2019 was pretty busy with Dreamforce, Monkey Run Morocco, French Touch Dreamin and Christmas/Holidays. I figured I&amp;rsquo;d get it written up in early 2020&amp;hellip;
Then 2020 happened&amp;hellip; and turned in to a complete dumpster fire. With everything going on, I was finding it difficult to find the time and motivation to write anything.</description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[ <p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/23b9a76b8b2a24bf3937cd648179c24f_badge.png" alt="Header Image"  />
</p>
<p>Normally, when I do a talk at Dreamforce, or another conference, I write a follow up blog post covering the same content. But the end of 2019 was pretty busy with <a href="https://www.salesforce.com/blog/dreamforce-2019-infographic/">Dreamforce</a>, <a href="https://www.theadventurists.com/adventures/monkey-run-morocco/">Monkey Run Morocco</a>, <a href="https://frenchtouchdreamin.com/">French Touch Dreamin</a> and Christmas/Holidays. I figured I&rsquo;d get it written up in early 2020&hellip;</p>
<p>Then 2020 happened&hellip; and turned in to a complete dumpster fire. With everything going on, I was finding it difficult to find the time and motivation to write anything. With the year almost over, and my blog revamped I knew I wanted to get it written.</p>
<p>Enough boring excuses. Here we go.</p>
<p>This is part one of the follow up post to my talk &ldquo;Microservices inside Salesforce With Platform Events and Change Data Capture&rdquo;. If you did catch my talk at Dreamforce 2019, or London&rsquo;s Calling 2020, I hope you enjoyed it. If not (or even if you did!), read on as I will cover the same topics here.</p>
<p>In part one we will cover the concepts, and in part two, the implementation. The first thing we need to understand is&hellip;</p>
<h3 id="what-are-microservices">What are microservices?</h3>
<p>The key to microservices is kind of in the name; small (micro) services. These services generally cover a specific functional area, or function and perform only that function. (e.g generating documents, or handling payments).</p>
<p>Ideally, these services are independently deployable, maintainable and testable. In larger applications or organisations these services are often developed and maintained by different teams, even using different languages or tech stacks. They are loosely coupled to other services and shouldn&rsquo;t have any &lsquo;hard dependencies&rsquo; on them.</p>
<p>When grouped together, all of these services, and their supporting infrastructure make up a larger application (e.g a Billing System).</p>
<p>A good analogy is the robots in a car factory. You have robots to weld the cars, robots to paint them and so on.  The painting robot is independent of the welding one. It does not know how to weld, or care how the car was welded. All it does is paint the car and send it on to the next station (micro service) in the factory (application)</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/abb-paint-atomizer.jpg" alt=""  />
</p>
<p>One of the key benefits of this is it means that when it comes time to upgrade the welding robot, the painting one does not need to be changed. Likewise if the painting robot needs to be changed, the welding robot doesn&rsquo;t care.</p>
<p>As you&rsquo;ve probably experienced, changing chunks of a normal &lsquo;monolithic&rsquo; type application can be painful, as it&rsquo;s often tightly connected to other parts of the application with no easy way to change just the one part you need to.</p>
<p>With a microservice approach, often these issues are either removed entirely, or heavily mitigated.</p>
<p>This is great and all, but these micro services need a way to communicate with each other, this needs to be in a &lsquo;common language&rsquo; they can all understand, so this brings us to&hellip;</p>
<h3 id="what-is-an-event-driven-architecture">What is an event-driven architecture?</h3>
<p>So as alluded to above, this approach hinges on these services having a common way to talk to each other.
If I&rsquo;ve got a service written in Apex on Salesforce, it has to know how to talk to a service written in NodeJS on Heroku, or something written in Java running on-prem.</p>
<p>This is where an event-driven architecture comes into play. It means that all of these services share a common eventbus on to which they publish (or push) to and subscribed to (or consume from), normally these events are segregated into topics or channels. I am going to use the terms publish, subscribe and topic to describe this from here on out.</p>
<p>The event bus sits in the middle of all of these microservices, services produce and subscribe to it to move data between them and perform their functions. The event bus also often manages things like queueing, replay of events, access to topics and security. Some common event buses are Apache Kafka, MQTT and CometD.
Salesforce of course also has its own event bus, the Enterprise Messaging Platform (often just called Platform Events, which uses CometD)</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/9d0edf028a3e0056757e93a3244a43de_salesforce-event-bus.jpeg" alt=""  />
</p>
<p>To better understand this concept, let&rsquo;s think for a second about twitter, it is like an event bus. If I see #Salesforce trending on twitter, I might click on that hashtag. This would mean I am &lsquo;subscribing&rsquo; to the Salesforce &rsquo;topic&rsquo;. If I then tweet &ldquo;#Salesforce is awesome&rdquo; I am then &lsquo;publishing&rsquo; to Salesforce &rsquo;topic&rsquo;, and anyone else following #Salesforce (aka subscribing to that topic) will see that message. Your microservices work the same way.</p>
<p>Each service will publish and subscribe to topics it &lsquo;cares&rsquo; about in order to function. It doesn&rsquo;t really have any knowledge of the other services, it just grabs the information it needs to do its job, and publishes its results for other services to do the same. This of course allows for services to be swapped/changed/enhanced without causing impact to other services within the application.</p>
<p>Another key feature of an event driven architecture is the ability for multiple subscribers to subscribe to the same topic. Often we only want one service producing to a topic, but there are exceptions to this rule.</p>
<p>For example, if I am building a billing system, perhaps I need to perform some tasks when an Opportunity is closed/won.
I might need to generate a PDF invoice to send to the customer or I might need to generate a packing slip to send to a warehouse.
If all of these subscribe to the &lsquo;Opportunity&rsquo; topic, then all of them can perform their task independently when they receive a closed/won opportunity message on that topic. Likewise, if I have one source of truth for Opportunity data (Salesforce) then I don&rsquo;t want other systems publishing data to the Opportunity topic.</p>
<p>If in the future I also need to activate the customer&rsquo;s new service in another system, the new system can simply listen to this topic! We don&rsquo;t need to make any changes to the existing systems, we can just &lsquo;bolt on&rsquo; this new system.</p>
<p>All of this sounds exciting right? So&hellip;</p>
<h3 id="how-does-this-relate-to-salesforce">How does this relate to Salesforce?</h3>
<p>Salesforce has a number of tools to help us out here, under the banner of &lsquo;The Salesforce enterprise messaging platform&rsquo;. This is often just called &lsquo;Platform Events&rsquo;, however Platform Events are just one of the tools available to us.</p>
<p>There are two we are going to cover in detail here, Platform Events and Change Data Capture.</p>
<p>So let&rsquo;s start with&hellip;</p>
<h4 id="platform-events">Platform Events</h4>
<p>Platform Events in this context is the term salesforce gives to custom topics. e.g topics we are developers are able to define and use for whatever we like.</p>
<p>We can define a platform event in much the same way as a Custom Object. They have a name like &ldquo;My_Cool_Event__e&rdquo; and have various field types that can be added to them (text, numbers, checkboxes, etc) which will contain the data for subscribers to use, or for publishers to populate.</p>
<p>Once we have defined our platform event &rsquo;topic&rsquo;, we can then publish events to it. This can be done from within Apex code, from processes or flow, or via Salesforce APIs from external services.</p>
<p>We can also subscribe to events from Apex triggers, processes, flows, lightning and visualforce components, or in external services via CometD.</p>
<p>Platform events are the most flexible kind of event, as they can be defined to contain any information we want, and be published or subscribed through a number of different methods.</p>
<p>There however is another very useful kind of event, these are&hellip;</p>
<h4 id="change-data-capture">Change Data Capture</h4>
<p>Change data capture (CDC) is a feature of Salesforce that publishes &lsquo;change events&rsquo;, These events represent changes to Salesforce records. Things that are classified as changes, and thus are published include creation of a record, updating a record, and deleting or undeleting a record. Once enabled for an object, these events are automatically published by Salesforce.</p>
<p>Change data capture is similar in a lot of ways to Platform Events and, in fact, uses the same underlying bus. The main difference is that publication of these events is done automatically by salesforce, and the layout of data within them (their schema) is unable to be changed by us. We can, however, subscribe to these events in the exact same way as a Platform Event.</p>
<p>Why is CDC important? Well it means that we can subscribe to any change in data across Salesforce, so in our billing example above, we don&rsquo;t need to define our own &lsquo;Opportunity&rsquo; event, we can simply enable CDC and subscribe to the events we need.</p>
<p>Now that we know about CDC, we need to&hellip;</p>
<h4 id="put-it-all-together">Put it all together</h4>
<p>We know that the &lsquo;Salesforce Enterprise Messaging Platform&rsquo; is our event bus. It is a part of Salesforce, and our publishers and subscribers (aka our micro services) need to be able to access it. For services on platform, it&rsquo;s easy.</p>
<p>There is nothing special that needs to happen (aside from creating Platform Events or enabling CDC), you just need to build them. It&rsquo;s slightly harder with Services outside of Salesforce. They need users accounts, and the appropriate level of access and your micro services needs to understand how to publish or subscribe to events (more on this in part two&hellip;)</p>
<p>We also know that our topics are Platform Events (if defined by us) or Change Data Capture (defined by Salesforce). We know that we can subscribe to both CDC and Platform Events in a variety of ways both on and off platform. We also know that we can publish Platform Events in a number of ways both on and off platform. Finally, we know that CDC events are published for us by Salesforce (once enabled).</p>
<h3 id="conclusion-and-further-reading">Conclusion and Further Reading</h3>
<p>In part one, we covered the main concepts, microservices and event driven architecture. How they work together and how they apply to Salesforce with Platform Events and Change Data Capture.</p>
<p>In part two we will cover how to build an application with these concepts, including how to swap out a service within that application to an off-platform version!</p>
<p>I hope you&rsquo;ve found this informative, and if you&rsquo;ve got any questions or comments, please send me a tweet <a href="https://twitter.com/mickwheelz_">@mickwheelz_</a>. If you want to learn more in the meantime, check out the links below;</p>
<p><a href="https://developer.salesforce.com/blogs/2018/07/which-streaming-event-do-i-use.html">Salesforce Blog - Which Streaming Event Do I Use?</a></p>
<p><a href="https://trailhead.salesforce.com/content/learn/modules/platform_events_basics">Trailhead - Platform Event Basics</a></p>
 ]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a information display for my CRF250L</title>
      <link>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2020-11-21-building-a-information-display-for-my-crf250l/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>me@sophi.ee (Sophie 🌸)</author>
      <guid>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2020-11-21-building-a-information-display-for-my-crf250l/</guid>
      <description>One of the small handful of motorcycles I own is a 2015 Honda CRF250L. I bought it after doing the Monkey Run Morocco in 2019 (maybe I should write about that one day&amp;hellip;) and realising this whole off road / adventure motorcycling thing is a lot of fun.
The CRF250L is an excellent beginners adventure bike. It&amp;rsquo;s lightweight, easy to ride and decent off road. It&amp;rsquo;s not an Africa Twin by any stretch, but for someone like me who is starting out, it&amp;rsquo;s great.</description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[ <p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/assembled-version.jpg" alt="Header Image"  />
</p>
<p>One of the small handful of motorcycles I own is a 2015 Honda CRF250L. I bought it after doing the Monkey Run Morocco in 2019 (maybe I should write about that one day&hellip;) and realising this whole off road / adventure motorcycling thing is a lot of fun.</p>
<p>The CRF250L is an excellent beginners adventure bike. It&rsquo;s lightweight, easy to ride and decent off road. It&rsquo;s not an Africa Twin by any stretch, but for someone like me who is starting out, it&rsquo;s great.</p>
<p>That said, there is room for improvement. The bike had a few choice mods when I bought it. Things like a smaller front sprocket (for a bit more low down torque), aftermarket air filter, bar risers, heated grips, hand guards, foldable mirrors and a rear rack.</p>
<p>One of the things I disliked about the bike was how basic its dash was. It has no tach and no temp gauge. You get speed, fuel, time and some lights&hellip; that&rsquo;s it.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/dash-stock.jpg" alt="stock-dash"  />
</p>
<p>It has an over-temp light, and obviously you don&rsquo;t <em>need</em> a tachometer, but it is nice to have a better idea of what the bike is doing.</p>
<p>I wondered if, being a somewhat modern bike, there would be some sort of diagnostic port that I could connect to to get this data. As it turns out, there is!</p>
<p>&ldquo;Modern&rdquo; Honda motorcycles have a 4 pin connector called a HDS port. This is <em>similar</em> in function to the OBD port in a car. In fact that was one of the first approaches I looked in to, after finding <a href="https://www.lonelec.co.uk/Honda-4pin-OBD2-Adaptor">HDS to OBD adapter</a> cables online.</p>
<p>After further research (huge shout-out to the <a href="http://forum.pgmfi.org/">PGM-FI forums</a>) found that Honda does use a standard protocol (KWP2000), but most cheap ELM327 OBD adaptors (including the one I had) are incompatible with it, as it has a non-standard initialisation sequence. I did try it anyway, after making a cable (aka jamming some wires into the HDS port and clipping them to the ELM327 device) I was able to confirm it didn&rsquo;t work.</p>
<p>So I kept looking and stumbled across two things that made me realise this was possible. The first was the <a href="https://gonzos.net/projects/ctx-obd/">CTX-OBD</a> project that had a similar goal/idea to what I was hoping to do. The second was the KWP2000 library for arduino that Aster94 had on <a href="https://github.com/aster94/Keyword-Protocol-2000">GitHub</a>.</p>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t end up using the KWP2000 library (as it&rsquo;s only been implemented for Suzuki) but I did use the hardware (namely a <a href="https://www.st.com/resource/en/datasheet/l9637.pdf">L9637D</a> bus driver)</p>
<p>I was able to finally prove the theory with some very ropey code, an Arduino Nano and the L9637D.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/ardu-nano.jpg" alt="ardu nano"  />
</p>
<p>Once the excitement of seeing data from my bike&rsquo;s ECU being displayed on my laptop, I  had to think about how I would build the actual device.</p>
<p>For the display, I decided to use an cheap ILI9341 SPI display, as they are easy to work with and I had a few laying about. For the microcontroller I went with an ESP32. I could&rsquo;ve used the Arduino Nano, but the ESP gives me a <em>much</em> faster CPU, more memory, more peripherals and the option to use things like WiFi and Bluetooth in the future. They are also incredibly cheap and I had a few of them kicking around.</p>
<p>I put together a prototype using the ESP32, a display and the L9637D chip.</p>
<p>After much tweaking it all worked and I knew the design was viable, so I designed a PCB in Eagle CAD. I sent it over to PCBWay for fab (my first time using them) and a week or so later these turned up.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/pcbs.jpg" alt="pcbs"  />
</p>
<p>I was very happy with the PCBs. They did have a small mistake, which was entirely my fault and only required cutting a trace. After fixing that and soldering everything on, I was able to flash the firmware I&rsquo;d written and it was ready to go. I added a few more features like an external temperature sensor (using a DHT22) and a GPS module for speed/heading/etc.</p>
<p>I needed a case, so designed something basic in Fusion360 and 3D printed it. I decided to go with a generic GoPro style mount on the bottom, which I paired with a handlebar mount I had to mount it to the bike.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/assembled-version.jpg" alt="assembled-version"  />
</p>
<p>I mounted it to the bike, and lo and behold, it worked! I took the bike for a ride and discovered a few bugs in the firmware (like the speed being reported in KPH not MPH) but it actually worked!</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>I have done a much more technical write-up on the project&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/mickwheelz/Honda-Motorcycle-Dash">GitHub repo</a>, which includes a wiki.</p>
<p>So whats next? Well I&rsquo;ve designed a version 2 of the PCB, which has simpler power delivery, and uses a display directly mounted to it. I will cover this new version in a future blog! I also need to do some more work on the firmware, and the documentation, which will come in time.</p>
<p>This should work on other Honda bikes, so if you&rsquo;ve got a Honda made in the last 10 years or so, and give it a try please do let me know how you go!</p>
 ]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A RetroPie (or similar) controller for £5?!</title>
      <link>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2018-02-23-a-retropie--or-similar--controller-for--5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>me@sophi.ee (Sophie 🌸)</author>
      <guid>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2018-02-23-a-retropie--or-similar--controller-for--5/</guid>
      <description>I recently found myself in Poundland seeing what a humble pound coin could get me, aside from the usual cables, chargers and similar accessories I buy… seriously, they work fine and are only £1/£2, not to mention their chargers are far better than cheap ones you’d find on ebay! Check out this video from bigclivedotcom on the subject.
As I was browsing, I happened upon the £5(!) electronics/games section. There were a few XBOX360 games and such, but what caught my eye was this;</description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[ <p>I recently found myself in <a href="https://www.poundland.co.uk/">Poundland</a> seeing what a humble pound coin could get me, aside from the usual cables, chargers and similar accessories I buy… seriously, they work fine and are only £1/£2, not to mention their chargers are far better than cheap ones you’d find on ebay! Check out this video from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aS1pwoVdRh4">bigclivedotcom</a> on the subject.</p>
<p>As I was browsing, I happened upon the £5(!) electronics/games section. There were a few XBOX360 games and such, but what caught my eye was this;</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*kIpPi7OvFPmWQaea.png" alt=""  />
I forgot to take a photo at the shopIt is a Gioteck ‘Turbo Controller’ for the Nintendo Classic Mini. It looks basically like a NES controller with turbo buttons. Considering my <a href="https://retropie.org.uk/">RetroPie</a> setup at home, but having no idea of the protocol/connector it used, I decided it was worth the sacrifice of £5 to find out if I could make it work. You can also get these controllers from the likes of <a href="https://www.ebay.co.uk/itm/Gioteck-Turbo-Controller-for-Nintendo-Classic-Mini-From-the-Argos-Shop-on-ebay/362156662685?epid=719581866&amp;hash=item5452381f9d:g:9uUAAOSwXz9Zk3ZV">argos/ebay</a> (for £5.99, the horror!).</p>
<p>I got it home, opened it up and saw the Nintendo ‘<a href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/50067687ef8740a0d1f7b2c9c1c9d97c059c5ab3/687474703a2f2f696d672e67756e6f6f6b2e636f6d2f75706c6f61642f392f66342f39663436366534623231383832613534373363306136316137376135663136362e6a7067">nunchuck</a>’ style plug on the (surprisingly long) cable. This was a good start and I figured that it probably uses the same protocol as the Nunchuck or the Wii Classic Controllers and similar that use the same plug. Both of these use the I2C protocol and there are various libraries out there to allow them to be use with Arduino’s and compatible micro-controllers.</p>
<p>I was hoping there would be something similar for the Raspberry Pi, given it has an I2C bus built in, but unfortunately the only information I could find was on drivers for the Wii controller with a Nunchuck or Classic Controller connected to it, connected to the Raspberry Pi over bluetooth, which was no use to me as I don’t own a Wii controller.</p>
<p>So I decided to write my own ‘driver’ for it (more of a daemon actually!) and here is how I did it;</p>
<p>First thing I had to do was crack it open to see if I could find the pinout. Mercifully it was printed right on the board, along with several test points I plan to investigate later. I2C devices generally use four wires VIN (Power, 3.3v) GND (Ground), SDA (Data) and SCL/CLK (Clock).</p>
<p>In this case, VIN is red, GND is black, SDA is green and CLK is white.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*9Y9E1gI10CMLzdB8.jpg" alt=""  />
Controller PCB with connections labeledGiven that this experiment was so cheap, I simply cut off the nunchuck style plug to expose the wires and I then attached my own pin sockets/plug for easy connection to a Raspberry Pi or other devices.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*CRZBi799F60cyPli.jpg" alt=""  />
Controller with new Raspberry Pi compatible plugAdding the plug made it very easy to connect and disconnect it from the various raspberry Pi’s I used for testing, namely a Raspberry Pi 3 I use to run RetroPie in my lounge room, and a Raspberry Pi 0W that I used for headless testing/development.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*n1p1L6J8dGLDN6g4.jpg" alt=""  />
Connected to the Raspberry PiIf you didn’t want cut it up, you can get you could grab a ‘<a href="https://www.adafruit.com/product/345">Nunchucky</a>’ from adafruit and solder wires and an appropriate plug to that, or scavenge sockets from a broken system.</p>
<p>Once I had the new plug on it, I connected it to an Arduino nano to do some testing. I initially tried the <a href="https://github.com/AndrewMascolo/WiiClassicController">WiiClassicController</a> library to see if it used the same protocol as the Nunchuck/Classic Controller and luckily for me, it did. So now I had to work out a way to get that data into a useable form on the Raspberry Pi using its I2C bus.</p>
<p>Ideally you would write a kernel module in C for this, but given my very limited knowledge of C and desire to get it running quickly I had to pick something else. I am most comfortable with Java so my my first attempt was to write a simple app that used the PI4J and Robot libraries to take the data from the I2C bus and turn it in to keyboard commands. This was very quick and easy to write, but unfortunately was a failure as Robot on linux requires X11 to be running for it to work, and RetroPie does not use X11.</p>
<p>I looked around, and a good way to achieve keyboard emulation at a lower level was with the <a href="http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man2/ioctl.2.html">ioctl</a> call, and there happens to be an wrapper for it in NodeJS. I am not brilliant with JS but I have written node app’s before and figured it was going to be easier than learning C (which I do want to do at some stage!)</p>
<p>My first attempt was using the <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/virtual-input">virtual-input</a> library, but nothing I did would make it work with the Raspberry Pi. I could get it work fine on an ubuntu VM to send keystrokes, but never on the Pi.I saw that it was used in another project, <a href="https://github.com/miroof/node-virtual-gamepads">node-virtual-gamepad</a> which is a really cool project. So I tried it and it and worked fine on the Pi.</p>
<p>I then had a look through the source to see if I could extract its virtual keyboard code for use in my own project and after much wrangling, I got it to work! I used evtest to detect the virtual keyboard codes as they were sent by the virtual keyboard code.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*ZZ0tZyPLhwAIC9PD.png" alt=""  />
evtest runningThe next thing to do was integrate the keyboard code with the <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/i2c">I2C</a> library to come up with some sort of daemon that would interpret the commands sent from the controller over I2C into keypresses on the virtual keyboard, thus controlling the game.</p>
<p>There was also code for emulating joysticks/gamepads which I do plan to build in to the daemon, so that you can choose to emulate a keyboard or gamepad depending on your needs. But the first order of business was to get it working as a virtual keyboard.</p>
<p>Once I had both portions working, both I2C reading and virtual keyboard, i was able to combine them to build the daemon that will run in the background and interpret the data from the controller in to keyboard presses to control the Raspberry Pi.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*pap6tnW-2MmFfMPW.jpg" alt=""  />
Testing it out with a bit of MarioThe code and is available on my github <a href="https://github.com/mickwheelz/NintendoI2C-Node">here</a>, along with instructions on how to setup and use it. If you want more detail on how I built it, read on.</p>
<p>Once I had both the virtual keyboard and I2C code working combining them was relatively straightforward, but there were a few gotchas.</p>
<ol>
<li>As I learned from the Arduino library, the gamepad sends data in ‘packets’ of 6 bytes</li>
<li>When there is no buttons pressed, the result always begins with a 0x0 (0) with the packet looking like this (decimal);</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>[ 0, 0, 128, 128, 255, 255 ]</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>The gamepad sends a ‘heartbeat’ packet of 6x 0xFF (255) byte values every ~8 seconds and a randomly times packet that begins with 0x1 (1), these look like this (decimal);</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>[ 1, 0, 164, 32, 1, 1 ] [ 255, 255, 255, 255, 255, 255 ]</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>In the linux event subsystem when a key is pressed a 1 is sent and it will remain pressed until a 0 is sent for the same key, you can send multiple 1’s and 0’s at once</li>
<li>All 8 buttons are handed by the last two bytes in the array (5 and 6) and some buttons when pressed together send a new code if they are on the same byte. I had to test and map these out.</li>
<li>I needed to ensure that 2 buttons can be pressed at a time in order for the controller to be useful
Below is a table of the keys to their ‘bytes’ that I am using to detect keypresses;</li>
</ol>
<p>Button Position Hex Dec D-pad Up Byte 5 0xFE 254 D-pad Down Byte 4 0xBF 191 D-pad Left Byte 5 0xF3 253 D-pad Right Byte 4 0x7F 127 Start Byte 4 0xEF 239 Select Byte 4 0xFB 251 A Byte 5 0xEF 239 B Byte 5 0xBF 191</p>
<p>Given that some buttons share the same byte (such as A&amp;B) they give different results if pressed at the same time. Below is a table of the ‘Combination’ bytes and positions;</p>
<p>Combination Position Hex Dec A &amp; D-pad Up Byte 5 0xEE 238 B &amp; D-pad Up Byte 5 0xBE 190 Select &amp; Start Byte 4 0xEB 235 A &amp; D-pad Left Byte 5 0xED 237 B &amp; D-pad Left Byte 5 0xBD 189 D-pad Up &amp; D-pad Left Byte 5 0xFC 252 D-pad Down &amp; D-pad Right Byte 4 0x3F 63 D-pad Down &amp; Start Byte 4 0xBB 187 D-pad Down &amp; Select Byte 4 0xAF 175 D-pad Right &amp; Select Byte 4 0x6F 111 D-pad Right &amp; Start Byte 4 0x7B 123 A &amp; B Byte 5 0xAF 175</p>
<p>Once I had this information, the code itself is fairly simple.</p>
<p>It polls the controller every 10ms (this can be changed) for the 6 byte array. From that I build JSON object containing each button and its state (0 or 1). I then check this against the last iteration to see if its changed to detect a change in state of a button, if its changed I then set the key high or low using the virtual keyboard library, at the end of the iteration i pass the current button states in to the ‘old’ iteration variable and start again. Only if the key has changed from one iteration to the next do I send a key event to change its state in the events subsystem.</p>
<p>The daemon is designed to be run in the background upon boot of the system to register events from the controller and pass them to the virtual keyboard. I also noted that the controller can be connected and disconnected while the daemon is running with no ill effects.</p>
<p>Let me know if you found this useful or interesting, or if you have any suggestions on improving it!</p>
 ]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>…and now for no reason: Emoji’s in your Wi-Fi name!</title>
      <link>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2017-07-26--and-now-for-no-reason--emoji-s-in-your-wi-fi-name/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>me@sophi.ee (Sophie 🌸)</author>
      <guid>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2017-07-26--and-now-for-no-reason--emoji-s-in-your-wi-fi-name/</guid>
      <description>A while ago, I came across someone using emoji as a Wi-Fi network name (SSID), I tried to do the same on my wifi router (I wanted the delightful smiling poo emoji 💩) but my router, sadly wouldn’t let me.
I saw it again the other day, and I thought I’d have another try, after all this was years ago and I have a much newer router, and newer version of DD-WRT running on it.</description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[ <p>A while ago, I came across someone using emoji as a Wi-Fi network name (SSID), I tried to do the same on my wifi router (I wanted the delightful smiling poo emoji 💩) but my router, sadly wouldn’t let me.</p>
<p>I saw it again the other day, and I thought I’d have another try, after all this was years ago and I have a much newer router, and newer version of DD-WRT running on it.</p>
<p>But, I was rudely told that what I was trying to do was illegal.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*7O9VqnfAJytS4D_Z.png" alt=""  />
Not to be deterred, I thought I’d try changing it via SSH… but that was not to be either.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*36s-ge9mATw_oXVq.png" alt=""  />
Inserting the emoji returned “p)” which was not accepted, I did also try the unicode char for it “<a href="https://apps.timwhitlock.info/unicode/inspect/hex/1F4A9">U+1F4A9</a>” but that didn’t work either.</p>
<p>Turning to google, I wondered if anyone had done this successfully before, but all I could find was <a href="https://medium.com/@bcjordan/emojify-your-wi-fi-c01f4ac0b0ab">this</a> article, This was done on the same model of wireless router as I own, but using the stock firmware.</p>
<p>But it did give me a good idea… So taking the same approach as in the article, but skipping straight to the server-side method, I used chrome dev tools to inspect the request;</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*lGdx0AmXnYqGfhyj.png" alt=""  />
So that is all well and good, but I need to replicate the request with new parameters, so turning to postman</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*6P2BZxQ0gKk51kju.png" alt=""  />
Fingers crossed, I hit send on the request… and low and behold!</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*NHLy4UGtaN3i7JQq.png" alt=""  />
Success!</p>
<p>So far I’ve not had any issues with modern-ish devices finding/connecting to it, however I did leave the 2.4ghz radio of my wireless router alone, so that older devices can use it if need be.</p>
 ]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
