<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>electronics on Sophie&#39;s Space</title>
    <link>https://sophieis.lgbt/tags/electronics/</link>
    <description>Read the latest  electronics on Sophie&#39;s Space</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>me@sophi.ee (Sophie 🌸)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>me@sophi.ee (Sophie 🌸)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 15:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sophieis.lgbt/tags/electronics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Building a information display for my CRF250L</title>
      <link>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2020-11-21-building-a-information-display-for-my-crf250l/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>me@sophi.ee (Sophie 🌸)</author>
      <guid>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2020-11-21-building-a-information-display-for-my-crf250l/</guid>
      <description>One of the small handful of motorcycles I own is a 2015 Honda CRF250L. I bought it after doing the Monkey Run Morocco in 2019 (maybe I should write about that one day&amp;hellip;) and realising this whole off road / adventure motorcycling thing is a lot of fun.
The CRF250L is an excellent beginners adventure bike. It&amp;rsquo;s lightweight, easy to ride and decent off road. It&amp;rsquo;s not an Africa Twin by any stretch, but for someone like me who is starting out, it&amp;rsquo;s great.</description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[ <p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/assembled-version.jpg" alt="Header Image"  />
</p>
<p>One of the small handful of motorcycles I own is a 2015 Honda CRF250L. I bought it after doing the Monkey Run Morocco in 2019 (maybe I should write about that one day&hellip;) and realising this whole off road / adventure motorcycling thing is a lot of fun.</p>
<p>The CRF250L is an excellent beginners adventure bike. It&rsquo;s lightweight, easy to ride and decent off road. It&rsquo;s not an Africa Twin by any stretch, but for someone like me who is starting out, it&rsquo;s great.</p>
<p>That said, there is room for improvement. The bike had a few choice mods when I bought it. Things like a smaller front sprocket (for a bit more low down torque), aftermarket air filter, bar risers, heated grips, hand guards, foldable mirrors and a rear rack.</p>
<p>One of the things I disliked about the bike was how basic its dash was. It has no tach and no temp gauge. You get speed, fuel, time and some lights&hellip; that&rsquo;s it.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/dash-stock.jpg" alt="stock-dash"  />
</p>
<p>It has an over-temp light, and obviously you don&rsquo;t <em>need</em> a tachometer, but it is nice to have a better idea of what the bike is doing.</p>
<p>I wondered if, being a somewhat modern bike, there would be some sort of diagnostic port that I could connect to to get this data. As it turns out, there is!</p>
<p>&ldquo;Modern&rdquo; Honda motorcycles have a 4 pin connector called a HDS port. This is <em>similar</em> in function to the OBD port in a car. In fact that was one of the first approaches I looked in to, after finding <a href="https://www.lonelec.co.uk/Honda-4pin-OBD2-Adaptor">HDS to OBD adapter</a> cables online.</p>
<p>After further research (huge shout-out to the <a href="http://forum.pgmfi.org/">PGM-FI forums</a>) found that Honda does use a standard protocol (KWP2000), but most cheap ELM327 OBD adaptors (including the one I had) are incompatible with it, as it has a non-standard initialisation sequence. I did try it anyway, after making a cable (aka jamming some wires into the HDS port and clipping them to the ELM327 device) I was able to confirm it didn&rsquo;t work.</p>
<p>So I kept looking and stumbled across two things that made me realise this was possible. The first was the <a href="https://gonzos.net/projects/ctx-obd/">CTX-OBD</a> project that had a similar goal/idea to what I was hoping to do. The second was the KWP2000 library for arduino that Aster94 had on <a href="https://github.com/aster94/Keyword-Protocol-2000">GitHub</a>.</p>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t end up using the KWP2000 library (as it&rsquo;s only been implemented for Suzuki) but I did use the hardware (namely a <a href="https://www.st.com/resource/en/datasheet/l9637.pdf">L9637D</a> bus driver)</p>
<p>I was able to finally prove the theory with some very ropey code, an Arduino Nano and the L9637D.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/ardu-nano.jpg" alt="ardu nano"  />
</p>
<p>Once the excitement of seeing data from my bike&rsquo;s ECU being displayed on my laptop, I  had to think about how I would build the actual device.</p>
<p>For the display, I decided to use an cheap ILI9341 SPI display, as they are easy to work with and I had a few laying about. For the microcontroller I went with an ESP32. I could&rsquo;ve used the Arduino Nano, but the ESP gives me a <em>much</em> faster CPU, more memory, more peripherals and the option to use things like WiFi and Bluetooth in the future. They are also incredibly cheap and I had a few of them kicking around.</p>
<p>I put together a prototype using the ESP32, a display and the L9637D chip.</p>
<p>After much tweaking it all worked and I knew the design was viable, so I designed a PCB in Eagle CAD. I sent it over to PCBWay for fab (my first time using them) and a week or so later these turned up.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/pcbs.jpg" alt="pcbs"  />
</p>
<p>I was very happy with the PCBs. They did have a small mistake, which was entirely my fault and only required cutting a trace. After fixing that and soldering everything on, I was able to flash the firmware I&rsquo;d written and it was ready to go. I added a few more features like an external temperature sensor (using a DHT22) and a GPS module for speed/heading/etc.</p>
<p>I needed a case, so designed something basic in Fusion360 and 3D printed it. I decided to go with a generic GoPro style mount on the bottom, which I paired with a handlebar mount I had to mount it to the bike.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/assembled-version.jpg" alt="assembled-version"  />
</p>
<p>I mounted it to the bike, and lo and behold, it worked! I took the bike for a ride and discovered a few bugs in the firmware (like the speed being reported in KPH not MPH) but it actually worked!</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>I have done a much more technical write-up on the project&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/mickwheelz/Honda-Motorcycle-Dash">GitHub repo</a>, which includes a wiki.</p>
<p>So whats next? Well I&rsquo;ve designed a version 2 of the PCB, which has simpler power delivery, and uses a display directly mounted to it. I will cover this new version in a future blog! I also need to do some more work on the firmware, and the documentation, which will come in time.</p>
<p>This should work on other Honda bikes, so if you&rsquo;ve got a Honda made in the last 10 years or so, and give it a try please do let me know how you go!</p>
 ]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A RetroPie (or similar) controller for £5?!</title>
      <link>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2018-02-23-a-retropie--or-similar--controller-for--5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>me@sophi.ee (Sophie 🌸)</author>
      <guid>https://sophieis.lgbt/posts/2018-02-23-a-retropie--or-similar--controller-for--5/</guid>
      <description>I recently found myself in Poundland seeing what a humble pound coin could get me, aside from the usual cables, chargers and similar accessories I buy… seriously, they work fine and are only £1/£2, not to mention their chargers are far better than cheap ones you’d find on ebay! Check out this video from bigclivedotcom on the subject.
As I was browsing, I happened upon the £5(!) electronics/games section. There were a few XBOX360 games and such, but what caught my eye was this;</description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[ <p>I recently found myself in <a href="https://www.poundland.co.uk/">Poundland</a> seeing what a humble pound coin could get me, aside from the usual cables, chargers and similar accessories I buy… seriously, they work fine and are only £1/£2, not to mention their chargers are far better than cheap ones you’d find on ebay! Check out this video from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aS1pwoVdRh4">bigclivedotcom</a> on the subject.</p>
<p>As I was browsing, I happened upon the £5(!) electronics/games section. There were a few XBOX360 games and such, but what caught my eye was this;</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*kIpPi7OvFPmWQaea.png" alt=""  />
I forgot to take a photo at the shopIt is a Gioteck ‘Turbo Controller’ for the Nintendo Classic Mini. It looks basically like a NES controller with turbo buttons. Considering my <a href="https://retropie.org.uk/">RetroPie</a> setup at home, but having no idea of the protocol/connector it used, I decided it was worth the sacrifice of £5 to find out if I could make it work. You can also get these controllers from the likes of <a href="https://www.ebay.co.uk/itm/Gioteck-Turbo-Controller-for-Nintendo-Classic-Mini-From-the-Argos-Shop-on-ebay/362156662685?epid=719581866&amp;hash=item5452381f9d:g:9uUAAOSwXz9Zk3ZV">argos/ebay</a> (for £5.99, the horror!).</p>
<p>I got it home, opened it up and saw the Nintendo ‘<a href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/50067687ef8740a0d1f7b2c9c1c9d97c059c5ab3/687474703a2f2f696d672e67756e6f6f6b2e636f6d2f75706c6f61642f392f66342f39663436366534623231383832613534373363306136316137376135663136362e6a7067">nunchuck</a>’ style plug on the (surprisingly long) cable. This was a good start and I figured that it probably uses the same protocol as the Nunchuck or the Wii Classic Controllers and similar that use the same plug. Both of these use the I2C protocol and there are various libraries out there to allow them to be use with Arduino’s and compatible micro-controllers.</p>
<p>I was hoping there would be something similar for the Raspberry Pi, given it has an I2C bus built in, but unfortunately the only information I could find was on drivers for the Wii controller with a Nunchuck or Classic Controller connected to it, connected to the Raspberry Pi over bluetooth, which was no use to me as I don’t own a Wii controller.</p>
<p>So I decided to write my own ‘driver’ for it (more of a daemon actually!) and here is how I did it;</p>
<p>First thing I had to do was crack it open to see if I could find the pinout. Mercifully it was printed right on the board, along with several test points I plan to investigate later. I2C devices generally use four wires VIN (Power, 3.3v) GND (Ground), SDA (Data) and SCL/CLK (Clock).</p>
<p>In this case, VIN is red, GND is black, SDA is green and CLK is white.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*9Y9E1gI10CMLzdB8.jpg" alt=""  />
Controller PCB with connections labeledGiven that this experiment was so cheap, I simply cut off the nunchuck style plug to expose the wires and I then attached my own pin sockets/plug for easy connection to a Raspberry Pi or other devices.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*CRZBi799F60cyPli.jpg" alt=""  />
Controller with new Raspberry Pi compatible plugAdding the plug made it very easy to connect and disconnect it from the various raspberry Pi’s I used for testing, namely a Raspberry Pi 3 I use to run RetroPie in my lounge room, and a Raspberry Pi 0W that I used for headless testing/development.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*n1p1L6J8dGLDN6g4.jpg" alt=""  />
Connected to the Raspberry PiIf you didn’t want cut it up, you can get you could grab a ‘<a href="https://www.adafruit.com/product/345">Nunchucky</a>’ from adafruit and solder wires and an appropriate plug to that, or scavenge sockets from a broken system.</p>
<p>Once I had the new plug on it, I connected it to an Arduino nano to do some testing. I initially tried the <a href="https://github.com/AndrewMascolo/WiiClassicController">WiiClassicController</a> library to see if it used the same protocol as the Nunchuck/Classic Controller and luckily for me, it did. So now I had to work out a way to get that data into a useable form on the Raspberry Pi using its I2C bus.</p>
<p>Ideally you would write a kernel module in C for this, but given my very limited knowledge of C and desire to get it running quickly I had to pick something else. I am most comfortable with Java so my my first attempt was to write a simple app that used the PI4J and Robot libraries to take the data from the I2C bus and turn it in to keyboard commands. This was very quick and easy to write, but unfortunately was a failure as Robot on linux requires X11 to be running for it to work, and RetroPie does not use X11.</p>
<p>I looked around, and a good way to achieve keyboard emulation at a lower level was with the <a href="http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man2/ioctl.2.html">ioctl</a> call, and there happens to be an wrapper for it in NodeJS. I am not brilliant with JS but I have written node app’s before and figured it was going to be easier than learning C (which I do want to do at some stage!)</p>
<p>My first attempt was using the <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/virtual-input">virtual-input</a> library, but nothing I did would make it work with the Raspberry Pi. I could get it work fine on an ubuntu VM to send keystrokes, but never on the Pi.I saw that it was used in another project, <a href="https://github.com/miroof/node-virtual-gamepads">node-virtual-gamepad</a> which is a really cool project. So I tried it and it and worked fine on the Pi.</p>
<p>I then had a look through the source to see if I could extract its virtual keyboard code for use in my own project and after much wrangling, I got it to work! I used evtest to detect the virtual keyboard codes as they were sent by the virtual keyboard code.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*ZZ0tZyPLhwAIC9PD.png" alt=""  />
evtest runningThe next thing to do was integrate the keyboard code with the <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/i2c">I2C</a> library to come up with some sort of daemon that would interpret the commands sent from the controller over I2C into keypresses on the virtual keyboard, thus controlling the game.</p>
<p>There was also code for emulating joysticks/gamepads which I do plan to build in to the daemon, so that you can choose to emulate a keyboard or gamepad depending on your needs. But the first order of business was to get it working as a virtual keyboard.</p>
<p>Once I had both portions working, both I2C reading and virtual keyboard, i was able to combine them to build the daemon that will run in the background and interpret the data from the controller in to keyboard presses to control the Raspberry Pi.</p>
<p>
<img class="enclosure" src="/img/0*pap6tnW-2MmFfMPW.jpg" alt=""  />
Testing it out with a bit of MarioThe code and is available on my github <a href="https://github.com/mickwheelz/NintendoI2C-Node">here</a>, along with instructions on how to setup and use it. If you want more detail on how I built it, read on.</p>
<p>Once I had both the virtual keyboard and I2C code working combining them was relatively straightforward, but there were a few gotchas.</p>
<ol>
<li>As I learned from the Arduino library, the gamepad sends data in ‘packets’ of 6 bytes</li>
<li>When there is no buttons pressed, the result always begins with a 0x0 (0) with the packet looking like this (decimal);</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>[ 0, 0, 128, 128, 255, 255 ]</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>The gamepad sends a ‘heartbeat’ packet of 6x 0xFF (255) byte values every ~8 seconds and a randomly times packet that begins with 0x1 (1), these look like this (decimal);</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>[ 1, 0, 164, 32, 1, 1 ] [ 255, 255, 255, 255, 255, 255 ]</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>In the linux event subsystem when a key is pressed a 1 is sent and it will remain pressed until a 0 is sent for the same key, you can send multiple 1’s and 0’s at once</li>
<li>All 8 buttons are handed by the last two bytes in the array (5 and 6) and some buttons when pressed together send a new code if they are on the same byte. I had to test and map these out.</li>
<li>I needed to ensure that 2 buttons can be pressed at a time in order for the controller to be useful
Below is a table of the keys to their ‘bytes’ that I am using to detect keypresses;</li>
</ol>
<p>Button Position Hex Dec D-pad Up Byte 5 0xFE 254 D-pad Down Byte 4 0xBF 191 D-pad Left Byte 5 0xF3 253 D-pad Right Byte 4 0x7F 127 Start Byte 4 0xEF 239 Select Byte 4 0xFB 251 A Byte 5 0xEF 239 B Byte 5 0xBF 191</p>
<p>Given that some buttons share the same byte (such as A&amp;B) they give different results if pressed at the same time. Below is a table of the ‘Combination’ bytes and positions;</p>
<p>Combination Position Hex Dec A &amp; D-pad Up Byte 5 0xEE 238 B &amp; D-pad Up Byte 5 0xBE 190 Select &amp; Start Byte 4 0xEB 235 A &amp; D-pad Left Byte 5 0xED 237 B &amp; D-pad Left Byte 5 0xBD 189 D-pad Up &amp; D-pad Left Byte 5 0xFC 252 D-pad Down &amp; D-pad Right Byte 4 0x3F 63 D-pad Down &amp; Start Byte 4 0xBB 187 D-pad Down &amp; Select Byte 4 0xAF 175 D-pad Right &amp; Select Byte 4 0x6F 111 D-pad Right &amp; Start Byte 4 0x7B 123 A &amp; B Byte 5 0xAF 175</p>
<p>Once I had this information, the code itself is fairly simple.</p>
<p>It polls the controller every 10ms (this can be changed) for the 6 byte array. From that I build JSON object containing each button and its state (0 or 1). I then check this against the last iteration to see if its changed to detect a change in state of a button, if its changed I then set the key high or low using the virtual keyboard library, at the end of the iteration i pass the current button states in to the ‘old’ iteration variable and start again. Only if the key has changed from one iteration to the next do I send a key event to change its state in the events subsystem.</p>
<p>The daemon is designed to be run in the background upon boot of the system to register events from the controller and pass them to the virtual keyboard. I also noted that the controller can be connected and disconnected while the daemon is running with no ill effects.</p>
<p>Let me know if you found this useful or interesting, or if you have any suggestions on improving it!</p>
 ]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
